乔·麦克米伦是什么时候来找你
When did Joe MacMillan come to you with the idea
逆向工程IBM个人电脑的
to reverse engineer the IBM PC?
这个陈述不太准确
Um, that's factually incorrect.
是约翰·博斯沃思和内森·卡迪夫于今年
John Bosworth and Nathan Cardiff approached me
4月4日来找我商讨新个人电脑项目的事
about a new PC program on April 4th of this year.
我理理清楚
Let me get this straight.
他们雇你克隆我们的BIOS代码
You were hired to write a replica of our BIOS code,
但你并不会看我们的BIOS代码
but you won't be looking at our BIOS code.
你看起来人不错
You seem like a good kid.
我们要的也不是你  所以你就...
We're not here for you, so why don't you just...
我不用看你们的BIOS代码
Look, I don't need to look at your BIOS
因为那种垃圾我也没兴趣抄
because I'm not interested in copying garbage.
当然  也许没有16位总线
Sure, I might decide I want to spend the rest of my natural life
我执行个指令得等上一辈子
waiting to move an instruction without a 16-bit bus,
除此之外  我才不会看你们的代码
but other than that, I'm not looking at that binder.
-那为什么找你呢  -什么意思
- Then why you? - Excuse me?
为什么找你
Why you?
你是大型机软件开发工程师
You're a mainframe software engineer.
你又不会搭建新东西
You certainly don't build anything.
克拉克先生无需解释为什么...
Mr. Clark does not have to theorize as to why...
我的微机经验比你们所有人都丰富
I have more microcomputing experience than anyone here.
我想问清楚
Just so I understand,
你是说你在此领域的失败经验
you're saying that your past failures in this area
却使你有资格领军卡迪夫的个人电脑项目吗
somehow qualify you to spearhead the Cardiff PC program?
你觉得他们要雇她多久
What do you think they got her on for?
-四周  五周  -直到她写完BIOS代码
- Four, five, weeks? - However long it takes to finish the BIOS.
我先说清楚  如果你真看代码簿了
Just so we're clear, if you do decide to open this binder,
你就是头一个进监狱的
you'll be the first one that goes to jail.
马上该你了
You're up right now.
这不对  这样不对
That ain't right. It just ain't right.
进去照着商量好的说就行了
Just go in, stick to the script.
你觉得那么容易吗
You think this is easy?
复述一堆谎话
Parrot out a couple of outright lies,
然后回家闷头大睡吗
go home, sleep like a champ.
你还嫩得很  孩子
You got a lot to learn, son.
你以为IBM没撒过谎吗
You don't think IBM's ever lied?
我不知道  我也不在乎
I don't know. Don't care.
你得明白
Look, I need you to understand
我的所作所为都是为大局考虑
that I did what I did because it was right,
不只为了我  还为了你和所有人
not just for me, for you, for everybody.
要是我上周来  客气地问你
If I'd come in here a week ago and asked nicely,
你早就大笑着把我轰出去了
you'd have laughed me out of the room.
我会一脚把你踢出去
I'd have kicked your ass is what I woulda done.
现在也没准
And I still might.
戴尔  没带律师吗
Dale, no lawyers.
何必
Why?
我知道你要说什么
I know what you're gonna say.
你把你的人教导的不错
You've coached your team well.
我们并没做出格的事
All we did was stay inbounds.
告诉波卡拉顿的小伙子们
You tell the boys at Boca Raton
位于福罗里达州  IBM个人电脑诞生地
他们编的BIOS不错
they've written a nice BIOS here.
这会是场硬战
It'll be tough to beat.
但放心  我们的代码不会有侵权的部分
But rest assured, ours will contain no copyrighted material,
卡梅伦·豪伊会在一个完全隔绝的无扰室内工作
Cameron Howe will be completely isolated in a clean room environment,
不会与戈登·克拉克有任何接触
she'll have no contact with Gordon Clark
也不会接触他的逆向工程成品
or his reverse-engineering work.
代码中的相似之处将纯属巧合
Any similarities in the code will be completely coincidental,
就像哥伦比亚数据产品公司
just like Columbia Data.
两家公司均通过逆向工程  发展出了不侵权的BIOS副本
就像康柏电脑
Just like Compaq.
你和我一样清楚法律漏洞
You know the legal loophole as well as I do.
说实话  这我都不在乎
Honestly, I don't care.
我更想知道
I'm more interested in
这一年半你到底去哪了
wherethe hell you've been the last year and a half.
你不辞而别
You left without saying good-bye.
跟你的新朋友提起过那天吗
Told any of your new friends about that day?
你们合计得再天衣无缝又怎样
Say all your ducks are in a row.
我们还是可以照样告你
Maybe we just sue you anyway.
拿文山纸海连轴诉讼活埋了你
Just bury you in paperwork and legal costs.
你看见外面坐着的那人了吗
You see that gentleman out there?
他是我们的专职法律顾问  巴瑞·希尔斯
That's our in-house counsel, Barry Shields.
卡迪夫电子每年要付给他五万五
He costs Cardiff Electric $55,000 a year,
不管你请来多少天兵天将
and no matter how many hundreds of lawyers you drop from the sky,
我们只用巴瑞
we're gonna stick with Barry.
就他一人
Just Barry.
活活累死他
We will ruin his life.
就算真闹到法庭上  你也输定了
And if this ever goes to trial, you'll lose...
因为说到底  你什么把柄都没有
'cause at the end of the day, you have nothing.
一路顺风
Have a nice flight.
-我们没事了吧  -好极了
- So, we're good? - We're perfect.
我去写BIOS代码  然后呢
So, hey, I write the BIOS code, then what?
我们到底想造什么
What exactly are we building?
速度翻倍  价格减半
这基本不可能
That's physically impossible.
这真的就是个物理方面的问题
I mean, it's literally a physics problem.
我糊涂了  全部目标就是这个
I don't understand. This is seriously all we're building.
你不明白  市场靠利润推动
Look, you don't get it. The market moves by increments.
下一款上市的电脑要么更快  要么更便宜
The next machine that hits the shelves is either faster or cheaper.
但是没法兼得
It can't be both, you know.
根本就不可能
That's impossible. It's--
你怎么想的  提高处理器主频还是...
What are you talking about, pure megahertz here, or--
没准我们可以
or maybe we could--
可以在硬件上下下功夫
we could crank up the crystal
或者从软件下手
or attack at the software.
乔  你的想法有意思  很有意思
Joe, that's interesting. That's really interesting.
慢着  什么  等等
Wait, what? Back up!
这根本什么都不是  陈词滥调啊
This is nothing. This is boring.
这就是割草机  或是微波炉
This is a lawn mower or a microwave.
看来你还是个空想主义者
Let me guess, you're one of those idea people.
你所谓的"空想"是指我知道
If by "idea people," you mean I'm familiar
没有在十年前就淘汰的古董技术吗
with technology that wasn't obsolete a decade ago.
你真的碰过电脑硬件吗
Have you ever even touched a piece of hardware?
你们这些自以为是的小屁孩都这毛病
See, that's the problem with you entitled school kids.
花花理论一套一套
You've got a lot of fancy theories,
但从没潜下心真正研究硬件
but you've never actually been close to the metal.
如果"纯理论"是不愿意
If real theory is that I want to do something
不管别人做什么
a little bit more than two
我们只管翻倍那么简单...
times everything that everybody else is doing!
电脑就该有照片级真实的显示器
Computers should have photo-realistic screens.
有百万像素  还能自主学习
They should have a million pixels and be self-learning
还能运行专家系统
and run expert systems.
能下棋赢过我
They should beat me at chess.
那超级电脑HAL是不是还该拥有情感
And maybe HAL can have human emotions, too,
出自《2001太空漫游》
能在我们睡觉时开太空船
and steer the ship while we're sleeping.
那我们就只跟风造个米黄的盒子吗
So we're just building another boring beige box?
造什么都轮不着你
You're not building anything, okay?
-那是我的事  -你这话什么意思
- I am. - What's that supposed to mean?
你俩怎么还在一个房间里
Hey, why are you two still in the same room?
不行  现在起我们光明正大
No, from here on in, we do this thing aboveboard,
完全依照法律
to the letter of the law.
所以  你俩哪怕上厕所路上
And that means you two don't so much as smile at each other
打个照面笑一笑都不行
on your way to the ladies' room.
好啊  快把她带走
Fine, get her out of here.
黛比  你能照顾下这位小麻杆吗
Debbie, can you deal with slim here?
你们的工作内容究竟是什么
So, what is it that y'all are doing for us again?
写BIOS代码
Writing BIOS code.
意思是基本输入输出系统
It's "Basic Input Output Software."
你开电脑时就先启动这个系统
It's what first runs when you turn the computer on.
就像字星那样吗
So, like WordStar?
一种文字处理软件
BIOS启动电脑
So, BIOS boots the computer,
让电脑可以加载操作系统
which allows you to load the operating system
然后才能运行字星
and then you can run WordStar.
然后我才能敲出一封情书吗
So I can write a little love letter to my boyfriend?
是这样吗
That right?
差不多吧
Yeah, something like that.
欢迎来到无扰室
Welcome to the clean room.
知道吗  桑格百货这周末买一送二
You know, there'sa three-for-one at Sanger's all weekend.
那儿的衣服挺不错的
They got great stuff.
你写代码时我得待在这儿...
So, I have to stay here while you write the--
一直在吗
The entire time?
是的  法律要求我在无扰室做记录
Yeah, I'm legally required to keep the clean room log.
不让你接触那位有问题的工程师
Maintain the Chinese wall between you and that tainted engineer.
好了
Okay, hey.
大家都听我说
Listen up here, y'all. Hey!
跟大家说点事
I'm gonna catch up on a few things here.
这是乔·麦克米伦
All right, this here's Joe MacMillan.
他是新的
He is the new-- ahem--
高级产品经理
Senior Product Manager
负责卡迪夫电子新成立的个人电脑部
at Cardiff Electric's new Personal Computer Division.
乔从IBM转投了我们  算是吧
Yeah, Joe comes to us from IBM, sorta.
别看他刚来不久
He's only been with us a short while,
却已经带来了不小的影响
but he's already made quite an impact.
-乔  要不要...  -谢谢  约翰
- Joe, you wanna-- - Oh, thanks, John.
我必须要说
And I'd be remiss if I didn't say
全靠你的信念  远见
that it wasn't your faith, your foresight,
还有  恕我说话粗
and, if you'll excuse me,
你有种才能走到今天
your brass balls that got us here.
多亏你对这个项目的支持
By moving forward with this endeavor,
卡迪夫电子将
you have helped establish Cardiff Electric
成为业界先驱  迈入21世纪
as an industry trailblazer well into the 21st century.
为约翰鼓鼓掌吧
A round of applause for John.
这一周里你们可能听到些传言
Now, you may have heard some rumors over this last week.
看到了些蓝西装的陌生人
Perhaps you saw some unfamiliar blue suits in the building,
跟我一样听到了传言
heard the same whispers I did.
"马上要有动作了"
"Change is about to come down."
我今天来告诉你们  传言是真的
Well, I'm here today to tell you that those rumors were true.
卡迪夫电子是要有动作了
Change is coming to Cardiff,
我非常荣幸地告诉大家
and I'm pleased to announce that each and every one of you
公司将锦绣前程  而且大家都有份
will have a role to play in this company's bright future.
告诉大家  个人电脑部只有两条规矩
Now, I've only got two rules for our new PC division.
一  大家尽情找乐子
One, let's have a lot of fun.
二
And, two...
大家一起赚大钱  好吗
let's make a lot of money, right?
如果两条都做到了
And if we get one and two right,
也许可以改变大家工作的方式
well, we just might change the way people work,
生活的方式
the way people live,
与人互动的方式
and how they interact with each other.
也许还能在宇宙中留下印记
We just might put a ding in the universe, right?
你叫什么
Hey, what's your name?
-塔拉  -塔拉  你好
- Tara. - Tara, so good to meet you.
-那个  -戈登  能说句话吗
- You know-- - Gordon, hi, can I just borrow you for a second?
-就一下  -好吧
- Just one second. - Yeah, sure.
好了  你在这儿
Here we are. This is you.
看看谁升职了呢
Look who's moving up in the world.
窗子什么的全有了
Now you got a window and everything.
乔布斯  "宇宙里留下印记"
Jobs, "Ding in the universe."
史蒂夫·乔布斯  苹果的总裁
Steve Jobs, the guy who runs Apple,
几年前说的
he said that a few years ago.
我知道  说得多好啊
Yeah, I know. Isn't it great?
回家吧  好好睡一觉
You should go home, get a good night's sleep.
明天很重要
You've got a big day tomorrow.
为什么
Why?
明天你要开始构筑未来
Well, tomorrow you start building tomorrow.
*利多好想念  离家的小船*
*Lido missed the boat that day he left the shack*
*时间刚刚够  赌赌老虎机*
*Just long enough to grab a handle off the top*
*下站去芝城*
*Next stop Chi-town*
*利多放下钱  图案轮轮转*
*Lido put the money down and let it roll*
*再干一份活  他说刚刚够*
*He said one more job oughta get it*
*最后来一发  便金盆洗手*
*One last shot 'fore we quit it*
*一票抵路费*
*One for the roa..*
她说有助思考
She says it helps her think.
这是你点的吧
I'm guessing this is you.
太棒了
Oh, awesome.
谢了  他会付钱的
Thanks. He'll pay for it.
想告诉我你在干什么吗
Do you wanna tell me what you're doing?
给台没人会在乎的机子写BIOS
Uh, writing BIOS for a machine no one's gonna give a shit about.
没错  没错
You're right. You're right.
谁在乎这台机子呢
Who cares about the machine?
重要的是将来使用它的人
What really matters are the people who will use it.
如果降低成本  就降低了入行门槛
If we lower the cost, we lower their barrier to entry,
而速度加倍  则效率也加倍
and by doubling the speed, we allow them to do twice as much.
这样就相当于使用我们电脑的人
So, now we've got twice as many people
翻了一番  使用时间长了一倍
using our computer for twice as long.
你对着镜子练过这段吗
You practice that in a mirror?
我觉得你根本不珍惜
Look, I don't think you appreciate
我们现在的机会
the opportunity we have here to--
我都听到了
Mm-mmm, I heard all about it.
"找乐子  赚大钱"  还有些别的废话
"Have fun, make money." And then a whole bunch of other shit
要么是你编的  要么就是剽窃的
that you either made up entirely or stole from someone else.
你不过就是个推销员
You're just a salesman.
怎么样
So?
我觉得  我不敢肯定
I think-- I'm not positive,
但我有充分理由相信
but I have good reason to believe that...
我们不会有事的
we're gonna be okay.
-那IBM和...  -走了
- So, IBM and-- - Gone.
乔是对的  我们把他们赶走了
Joe was right. We played 'em right out the door.
-那你打算...  -我明天开始
- So you're gonna get to-- - I start tomorrow...
还有了新办公室
in my new office.
还有窗子什么的
Window and everything.
看看你  大人物
Oh, look at you, big shot.
-孩子们在哪  -他们在隔壁玩  在...
- Where are the kids? - They're playing next door at the--
等等
Hang on.
我想把...
I'm trying to--
-去卧室吧  -好
- Let's go to the bedroom. - Okay.
我明天得带琼妮去看牙医
I have to take Joanie to the dentist tomorrow.
他们可能得拔一颗牙
They might have to pull a tooth.
你该顺道来趟卡迪夫
You should stop by Cardiff.
我得送她回学校
I'm gonna have to take her back to school.
得啦  我知道她讨厌牙医
Oh, come on. I know she hates the dentist.
也许完事后顺道来看爸爸算是个安慰呢
Maybe it'll be a treat to stop by and see her daddy afterwards.
再说  你可以看看我的新办公室
Besides, you can see my new office.
对了  你找了谁
Who'd you get, by the way?
写BIOS的人
To write the BIOS?
麦克米伦肯定准备好了人选
I bet MacMillan had some guy all lined up, right?
确实是
He did, yeah.
-是谁  -卡梅伦·豪伊
- Who? - Cameron Howe.
他什么来路
What's his background?
好像是奥斯汀科技
Austin Tech, I think.
如果你也认同  他肯定挺厉害
Well, he must be the real deal if you're on board.
是啊
Yeah.
总之  我把蓝色巨人的那些混蛋赶走了
Anyway, I chased them blue bastards out of town, I tell you what.
你能相信吗  野马队没有败绩
Can you imagine the 'stangs go undefeated
还是没进去佐治亚的比赛
and still miss out on Georgia?
想想看  迪科森去打糖缸杯Can you imagine Dickerson in the Sugar Bowl?
年度美国大学橄榄球大型比赛
他肯定打得他们屁滚尿流
Oh, he woulda run all over them dogs, huh?
不过麦基埃尼的臂力还是很强
McIlhenny still got a good arm on him, though.
我敢说他今年要是投个十来次
I tell ya, I bet he throws for 1,000 yards this year
能投出一千码
if he throws for a dozen.
是啊
Yeah.
让人有点跃跃欲试  是不是  卡尔
Makes you want to suit up. Doesn't it, Carl?
你当年也是个狠角色
You were a pretty damn good player in your day, you know?
你今年还打算投资
So you think you're gonna kick into
球员招募基金吗
the player recruitment fund this year?
我打算秋天大投一笔
I think I'm gonna kick in big in the fall.
不确定
Mm, not sure yet.
卡尔
Hey, Carl?
我们的系统你们用的怎么样
Hey, how we doing system-wise over at your place?
你知道我要干什么吗
Know what I'm gonna do?
我打算派几个人过去给你升个级
I'm gonna send over a couple boys with some upgrades,
确保系统运行万无一失
just, y'know, to make sure everything's running top-notch.
怎么样
How about that?
完全免费
You know? No invoices. Huh-uh. No.
就是出于友谊
Just a favor between two 'stangs.
真好
Great.
如果你识字  我走了
她人呢
Where is she?
不知道
I have no idea.
她倒是挺有意思的
She's kind of interesting, though, you know?
总穿着迷彩服
Wears those army clothes.
你出去透透气吧
Why don't you get some air?
以后我来应付她
I'll deal with her from now on.
我得做无扰室记录
I gotta maintain the clean room log.
巴瑞  你脸上画着蛋蛋呢
Barry, you've got balls on your face.
什么
What?
-她就交给我了  -我的脸怎么了
- I'll handle it from here. - I got what?
你好像认为你可以在这儿为所欲为
It occurs to me that you think you can do whatever you want here.
这儿不是你的游乐场
This isn't your playground,
而且你想错了
and contrary to what you might think,
我见过代码  不太像你正在写的东西
I know what code looks like, and this certainly isn't code.
没错
You're right.
你说对了
No, you're right.
这不是代码
Yeah, this isn't code.
你也看到了
As you can tell.
我在考虑为了对齐八进制边界
I'm trying to decide if we need to do this multiplication
是否需要进行乘法运算
in order to align on octal boundaries.
我认为  相信你也会同意
Now, my gut says, and I'm sure you'd agree,
如果将将二进制数左移三位
that we can do a shift-left-together three-bit-zero
右侧补零  不仅更快
fill to the right, which is faster
而且与英特尔80186中的累加器效果相当
and gives the same result on the accumulator on the 186,
不过我也不确定
but... I don't know,
你的意见如何呢
I'd love to hear your thoughts.
你想不出来了
You're stuck.
你知不知道你想干什么
Do you even know what you're trying to do?
好像你就知道似的
What, like you'd know?
让我想想
Give me a minute.
也许我能帮忙
Maybe I could help.
好啊
All right.
你干嘛
What are you doing?
我现在不想再思考这个了
I don't want to think about this anymore.
我需要放空头脑
I need to clear my mind.
那就休息一下
Then take a break.
比如跟黛比和其他员工一起去喝个汽水吗
Like, we can get a soda with Debbie and the rest of the 700 Club?
我和他们不一样
I'm not them.
你得上楼去  乖乖守着你的终端
You need to go upstairs, get back to your terminal.
那我们到底要不要做这个
So, are we gonna do this, or what?
卡迪夫电子  请问您找哪位
Cardiff Electric, how may I direct your call?
请稍等
Please hold.
我得再重申一遍我们完全不了解那个女孩
I'll state for the record again that we know nothing about that girl
也不知道她会做出什么事来
or what she's capable of.
没错  等她写完BIOS代码
You're right. Once she writes the BIOS code,
就让她走人
we should cut her loose.
什么意思
What do you mean?
等她完成BIOS代码
As soon as she finishes the BIOS code,
就不再有法律威胁  也就不需要她了
there's no more legal threat, we don't need her anymore.
哦  好吧  好的
Oh, well, okay, yeah. Yeah, good.
解脱了  我完全理解
Good riddance. Makes perfect sense to me, but
但眼下我们得让她留在无扰室
right now we need her in the clean room.
那就下楼去和她说
Then you go down and talk to her.
我都不能和她待在一个楼层
I'm not even supposed to be on the same floor as her.
她要是没在桌边敲键盘的话
Look, if she's not at her desk inputting keystrokes,
就没在写BIOS代码
then she's not writing BIOS code, okay?
我们要让她写BIOS代码
We need her writing BIOS code.
好吧
Okay.
妈妈  我想看看
Mommy, I want to see.
好吧  但是要快  好吗
Okay, but real quick, all right?
妈妈要回去上班
'Cause Mommy has to go back to work.
好了  进去  看一眼
All right, get in there. Let's take a look.
看到里面了吗
Do you see way back in there?
是的  原来是在那儿的
That's right. That's where it used to be.
像大峡谷一样
It looks like the Grand Canyon back there.
牙仙子今晚要有大收获了
Tooth fairy's got a good one for tonight.
舌头舔上去黏黏的
It feels slimy on my tongue.
宝贝  这么说好恶心
Sweetheart, that's gross.
来洗洗手
Go ahead, wash your hands.
洗好了吗  亲爱的
You all done, honey?
难刷的也要刷到哦
Gotta get the hard-to-reach ones.
琼妮
Oh, Joanie.
很抱歉  我们刚从牙医那儿回来
I'm sorry, we just came from the dentist.
我叫唐娜
I'm Donna.
卡梅伦
Cameron.
-疼吗  -不疼
- Oh, did that hurt? - Nope.
不会吧  拍个手
No way. Low five.
你可真勇敢啊  琼博士
You are braver than brave, Dr. J.
好啦女士们  周六球赛上见
All right, ladies. I'll see you Saturday for the soccer game.
维姬会带些她自己做的甜甜圈  好吃到爆
And Vicki's gonna drop off some homemade donuts that are pow!
好吃极了
Real good.
腿抬高  琼博士
Keep those knees high, Dr. J.
谢谢你  布莱恩
Thanks, Brian.
你觉得怎么样
So, what do you think?
新办公室  我自己的办公室
New office, my own office.
挺不错的吧
Not too shabby, huh?
你怎么了
You okay?
看牙的时间太长了
The dentist just went long.
说到这个  我们该回去了
Speaking of which, we should probably get back.
走吧  小捣蛋
You ready to go, monkey?
-好吧  -爸爸再见
- Okay, well-- - Bye, Daddy.
-再见  爱你哦  -我也爱你
- Bye, love you. - Love you, too.
干嘛啊
Dude.
我现在不需要你帮忙
I don't need your help right now.
它必须和我设想的一样
Look, I need this to be what I need it to be,
不是你想的那个样
not what you want it to be.
我需要一台可以运行IBM电脑程序
I need something that runs IBM PC programs
而且比IBM电脑还快的东西
faster than an IBM PC.
什么  我说了
What? I told them I wouldn't
-我不会看原码的  -要是时间充裕
- look at the original code.  - I'd let you do this yourself
我会让你独立完成的  但我们没时间了
if we had the time, but we don't.
我们要抓住这个稍纵即逝的机会
This gets us in a door that's closing fast.
之后就能实施你的伟大设想了
Once we're in, then we can handle those big ideas of yours.
是啊  但用了那些代码  我会进监狱
Yeah, if I copy that code, I go to jail.
IBM知道你会看的
IBM knows you're gonna look at this.
稍稍改动你的BIOS  避开麻烦
You change your BIOS just enough to stay out of trouble.
这样不出一年
Then, within a year,
我们的电脑就能和他们的平起平坐
our PC's on a shelf right next to theirs.
事情就是这样  来吧  干活儿吧
That's how this works. Come on, let's get in the game.
我在工作
I'm working,
你为什么不去做产品经理该做的
so why don't you go do whatever it is a product manager does?
天呐
Jesus.
真好吃
That was great.
能拿走了吗  吃完了吗
Can I take that? Are you done?
来  我来吧
Here, no, let me get that.
-不  我来吧  -不用  给我吧
- No, no, I got it. - No, let me get it.
谢了
Thanks.
你今天赶回去工作了吗
So, did you get back to work okay today?
3点过后才回去的
No, not till after 3:00.
幸好亨特没注意到
Thank God Hunt didn't notice.
卡梅伦是个女的  她是个女的
Look, Cameron's a girl, okay? She's a girl.
很抱歉  我不知道我为什么没跟你说
I'm sorry, I don't know why I didn't tell you that.
卡梅伦·豪伊是个女的
Cameron Howe is a girl.
乔雇的她  是他招进来的
Joe hired her. It was his call.
她虽说是女的  但她很怪
I said girl, but she's weird.
她确实在奥斯汀科技干过  但是...
She did go to Austin Tech, but--
我今天见到她了
I met her today.
那你为什么没说
Why didn't you say anything?
我为什么没说
Why didn't I say anything?
别担心  好吗
Look, don't worry, okay?
她只负责编写BIOS  然后就可以拜拜了
She's just writing the BIOS and then bon voyage.
好吧  希望乔选对了人
Yeah, well, let's just hope Joe was right.
打扰一下  小姐
Excuse me, miss?
小姐  我们需要谈谈
Miss, we need to talk to you.
干什么  好吧  我会付钱的
What? Okay, I'll pay for it.
我们有个提议  想跟你谈谈
We've got an opportunity we want to talk to you about.
-梅琳  -什么事
- Hey, Maylene? - Yes?
我怎么打不通卡尔·苏伯利的电话
Why can't I get Carl Suberry on the phone?
-我打他办公室试试  -没用  我试过了
- Let me try his office. - No, I tried his office...
还打过他家  以及他搞的那个车载电话
and tried his home and tried that car phone thing he's got.
EDS的杰夫·马丁呢
You know, what about Jeff Martin over at EDS?
电子数据系统公司
他的办公室说他还在开会
His office says he's still in a meeting.
克拉布系统公司也要离开
ClubSys is also pulling out.
打他电话  现在就打
Get him on the phone. Get him now.
是  先生
Yes, sir.
到底出什么事了
What the hell is going on?
那实际上...好的  先生
That is actually-- yes, sir.
已经有三家离开了
That's three off the board.
特纳  你干什么呢
Turner, what are you doing?
-怎么了  -IBM刚刚挖走了格兰杰
- What's happening? - We just lost Granger to IBM.
再打给他  再打...
Get him back on the phone. Get him back--
约翰  我们被人挖墙脚了
John, we're being raided.
是吉姆吗  吉姆  吉姆
Here, is that Jim? Jim, Jim, Jim.
吉米  你好啊  你好啊
Hey, Jimmy. Hey there, hey there.
我来跟你说  我跟你说说
Let me walk you back, now. Let me walk you back.
咱们生意做了11年了
We've been in business 11 years.
我可不希望你现在跑去IBM  拜托了  吉姆
I'd hate to see you hightail it to IBM now. Come on, Jim.
德州通讯在卸载所有的卡迪夫系统
They're de-installing all Cardifsystems at Texas Communications.
做点什么  戈登  天哪
Well, do something about it, Gordon. God--
给我重新接上吉姆
get Jim back on the line.
IBM在用30万的价格挖我们的墙角
IBM is undercutting us by 300 grand.
-现在就打给他  -好的  抱歉
- Get him on the phone now! - Okay, I'm sorry.
是比尔吗  比利  你好吗
Is this Bill? Hey, Billy, how are ya?
不不  我跟你说说  朋友  拜托了
No, no, let me talk you down now, friend. Come on.
等下
Hold on.
我们已经失去了美航  德通  克拉布系统
We've lost American Airlines, Texas Comm, ClubSys,
EDS  通用动力  还有其他七家公司
EDS, General Dynamics, and seven others.
-我来帮忙  -你才来十天  老天呐
- Let me help. - You've been here 10 days, for God's sake.
我了解这个行业
I know this business.
孩子  这个要的是人脉
Son, this is about relationships.
你是无法理解的
It's something you wouldn't understand.
说服他回来  闪开
Here, talk him back. Get out of my way.
比尔  是的
Bill, yeah.
卡尔  拜托
Carl, Come on, now.
卡尔  我是约翰啊
Carl, it's John here.
别这么对我
Don't do this to me.
卡尔  你是想让我求你吗
Carl. You gonna make me beg for this?
好吧
Fine.
好啊  你想弃船逃跑  爬去IBM那边
Fine, you wanna jump ship, you climb aboard with IBM,
悉听尊便
you be my guest.
不过你可别忘了
But you just remember
是我15年前给你的破公司电脑化的
it was me that computerized your outhouse of a company 15 years ago.
是吗  你这接球手烂透了
Yeah? Yeah, well, you were a lousy receiver whose ass
在场上都不会跑  就配坐冷板凳  卡尔
rode the bench better than he ever ran a damn route, Carl!
卡尔留不住了
Carl's a no.
那么  如果自动数据处理公司也要走
Then assuming ADP stays out...
共损失15个客户  最大的3个承担了
15 accounts lost, the top three of which represent
-我们68%的业务  -天呐
- 68% of our core billing.  - Oh, God.
那么这些挫折对
So, um, how severely will these setbacks
新的个人电脑项目影响有多大
affect the new PC program in terms of--
失去了这15个客户
Without these 15 clients,
再考虑到目前的营运成本和规模
and given it's current overhead burn and size,
卡迪夫电子还能维持
Cardiff Electric will be able to maintain operation for
稍少于两个月
a little less than two months.
两个月
Two months?
听到了吗  戈登
Did you get that, Gordon?
两个月
Two months?
艾伦的意思就是  我给你说清楚了
Because what Alan is saying-- and I wanna be clear on this--
就是IBM割了我们的喉咙
is that IBM just sliced our throats
要让我们像挂在钩子上的猪一样流血而死
and left us to bleed out like a hog on a hook,
到了下周  外面半数的人
and come next week, half those people out there,
都会失去工作  流落街头
they're gonna be out of a job, out on the street,
就为你的个人电脑
because of your personal computer.
你料到了吧
You know this would happen, though.
都是你计划的一部分
It's all part of the plan.
你有计划吧  乔
Tell me you have a plan, Joe.
你只是装相的吗
You were just pretending.
你就是那种
You're like one of those guys
看多了《麦田里的的守望者》
who goes out and reads "Catcher in the Rye" too many times
于是去枪杀披头士成员的人
and then decides to shoot a Beatle.
但这次  我是列侬
Only in this story, I'm the Beatle.
枪杀列侬的马克·查普曼痴迷于《麦田里的守望者》  并说他的作案动机就在书中
你就因为在杂志上读了我一篇文章
Because you read my article in a magazine.
你读了我的文章  就制定了一个计划
You read my article and you made a plan
却完全没有考虑到  会发生这种事...
and never once did you stop to think that something like--
你就带着那副讨厌的笑容  背别人的名言吗
you just recited your magic words with a big, awful smile?
在哪
Where is it?
在哪啊
Come on, where is it?
乔
Joe?
她哪去了
Where is she?
BIOS代码
The BIOS.
什么
What?
代码簿在哪  乔
Where's the binder, Joe?
你没把代码簿给她吧
Please tell me you didn't give her the binder.
汇编语言代码  IBM BIOS
The assembly language code, the IBM BIOS.
是你想要她回归正途的
Damn it, you wanted her back on track!
别都赖给我
Don't put this on me!
你基本上就是叫我拿给她了
You basically told me to give it to her!
我们要进监狱了
We're going to jail.
我们不会进监狱的  总有办法
We're not going to jail. There's always another move.
本来有的  就是别给她代码簿
There was. It was don't give her the binder.
或许她没走  或许她只是出去了
Maybe she's not gone. Maybe she just stepped out.
她不在这儿  也不在终端那儿
Look, she's not here. She's sure as hell not at her terminal.
我们又对这姑娘完全不了解
And since we know absolutely nothing about this girl,
除非她在女厕所  我们...
unless she's in the ladies' room, we are--
看啊
Look at this.
看她节省了...
The way she shortcuts the--
乱死了
What a mess.
不不
No. No.
不  这太聪明了
No, it's brilliant.
太棒了
It's brilliant.
要歇业啦  半价出售
那是放卡带的
That's a cassette system.
最新款的
New on the market.
我可以给你个折扣
I could take a little bit more off that for you.
经济不景气嘛
The day's marked for the recession, you know.
我也不是都想怪在滞胀头上
I mean, I don't mean to chalk it up to stagflation...
但我就是卖不动东西
...just can't seem to move any product.
这你也懂的吧
But you know how that is, right?
你也是个推销员
You're a salesman.
猜中了
I knew it.
果然是同路人
Birds of a feather.
你要关门了吗
So you're going out of business?
是啊  都记不住上次来客人是什么时候了
Yeah, I can't remember my last customer.
我不就是客人吗
I'm a customer.
推销一台音箱给我
Sell me a stereo.
好吧
Okay.
那是MRF1080
That's the MRF-1080.
真正的标准系统  可动线圈
True reference system, moving coil--
你的问题在哪
What's your problem?
-什么  -哪里出问题了
- Excuse me? - Where did you go wrong?
这家店为什么要歇业了
Why is this store going out of business?
肯定是有原因的  我想知道是为什么
There must be a reason. I want to know what it is.
我也不知道啊  这都是好东西
Beats me. I mean, the sound quality's great.
但大家就是不想...
People just don't wanna invest--
你就是没预料到
You just didn't see it coming.
伙计  我不知道你是闹得哪一出
Look, man, I don't know what this is about, but--
别这样
Hey, don't do that.
别动  你要动就得买  好吗
Hey, man, don't b-- you touch it, you gotta buy it, all right?
-你要弄坏喇叭的  -这就是你的工作吗
- You're gonna blow out the speakers! - Is that your job?
别这样
Come on!
你都预料不到  还在这儿干什么
If you can't see it, why are you even here?
我要报警了
I'm calling the cops.
我就待一会儿
This'll only take a minute.
挺舒服啊
Cozy.
你想干什么
What do you want?
可惜  我不能久留
Sadly, I can't stay.
今晚要坐9点半的红眼航班回去
Headed back on the 9:30 red-eye tonight.
走之前想了结最后一件事
Wanted to take care of one last thing before we left, though.
你离开的时候  并没有正式提交辞呈
When you walked out, you never gave formal notice.
欠付工资
Back wages.
你还有些没用过的假期
You had some vacation days in the system you never used.
总共615.38块
$615.38.
给你了
There you go.
615.38块
$615.38.
我给数据中心造成了超过两百万的损失
I did over $2 million worth of damage to the data center.
是啊  保险赔付之后
Yeah, well, after the insurance claim,
我们到头来还赚钱了
we ended up making money on that deal, too.
你与IBM的雇佣关系正式结束了
Consider your IBM employee file officially closed.
除非你今晚乘飞机跟我们回去
That is, unless you come back with us on the plane tonight.
我们都给你订座了  以防万一
We even booked you a seat, just in case.
商务舱  靠过道
It's business class, aisle.
挺不错的
Pretty nice.
我喜欢这里
I like it here.
我向你爸保证至少要试试的
Well, I promised your old man I'd give it a shot.
他应该会失望吧
I'd say he'll be disappointed,
但他已经够失望的了
but he's pretty disappointed already.
你现在可能喜欢这儿
You may like it out here now,
但是
but...
等他们发现你究竟是什么人之后
let's see what happens when they find out
再看看吧
what you really are.
在哪
Where is it?
-什么  -代码簿  BIOS
- Where's what? - The binder, the BIOS.
你给IBM了吗
Did you give it to IBM?
你们究竟找我来干什么
What am I really here for, huh?
四五周  直到我写完  是吗
What, four or five weeks, as long as it takes to write it, right?
然后呢  就打发我走吗
Then what? I'm gone?
什么  不是啊
What? No.
不是的  谁说的
N-no, no, who told you that?
便携
Portability.
得能让人随身携带
People need to be able to take it anywhere.
要加个把手
It's going to have a handle.
把手
A handle?
天呐  乔  真是佩服你
My God, Joe. I gotta give it to you.
这简直是扭转乾坤
This changes everything.
把手  真是革命性的主意
A handle. What a revolutionary idea.
那么还是要做个无聊破玩意的烂复制品
So it's still a piece of shit copy of a boring box?
乔  她把代码簿给了IBM
Joe, she gave the binder to IBM.
什么
You did what?
我没那么说啊
I never said I gave the binder to IBM.
-那在哪  -有什么要紧的
- Then where is it? - What does it matter?
本来我写完BIOS你们也要炒了我
You were gonna fire me after the BIOS anyway.
-你能怪我们吗  -那么是真的了
- Yeah, can you blame us? - Oh, so it's true.
好极了
Fantastic.
别担心  IBM说要给我份工作  三倍工资
Not to worry, IBM offered me a job, triple the salary, so--
太好了  那里可适合你了
Excellent, excellent. It's a great place to work.
我可以给你写封推荐信
I could write you a recommendation.
-真的吗  -是啊
- Would you? - That's right.
对了  你以前在那儿工作呢
That's right, you used to work at IBM.
那是你跑来这儿
That was before you came here
毁掉好几个人的生活  和一家公司之前
and ruined several people's lives and an entire company.
我来之前  你在酗酒  什么都不做
Before me, you were boozing, not building,
是个怕老婆的窝囊废
and your balls were in a box by your wife's bedside table.
够了
Stop it, man!
天呐
Holy shit.
我那年9岁
I was nine.
我学校的几个男生以前会...
There were some boys at my school who used to...
追赶我
chase me.
我不像他们那么关心纽约巨人队
I didn't care about the New York Giants like they did.
我关注的是旅行者1号I cared about Sputnik.
前苏联人造卫星
我为之疯狂  充满激情
I was nuts about it. I was passionate.
但没人告诉我
Nobody told me yet that
成年人不该有这种感觉
adults are supposed to be ashamed of those feelings.
小马队击败巨人队的那晚  我得到了这个教训
I learned that lesson the night the Colts beat the Giants.
58年的锦标赛  史上最棒的一场比赛
'58 Championship, greatest game ever played,
我根本没看
and I didn't see a single snap.
我重伤躺在圣彼得医院
I was hooked up to machines at St. Peter's.
直到今天  我也不怪他们
To this day, I don't blame them.
我觉得他们并非有意把我追下屋顶的
I don't think they meant to chase me off the roof.
离开IBM之后  我走遍全国
After IBM, I went across the country
想寻找答案
just looking for answers.
我读了你的文章  就一直魂牵梦绕
I'd read your article and I couldn't stop thinking about it.
开放式结构  这个想法
Open architecture, the idea of it.
作为一种生活方式
As a way of life.
让我夜不能寐  重新变成了那个执著的孩子
It kept me up at night. It made me that kid again,
我去计算机分销商展览找你
and I tracked you down to COMDEX
看着他们把你和
and watched as they chased you, too,
你精巧的机器也追下了悬崖
and your beautiful machine right off the ledge.
你  我看见你的时候
And you, when I saw you,
你的一切都让其他人害怕
everything about you threatens people.
我觉得或许我们能做到
I thought that maybe we could do this
就因为我们都是不按常理出牌的人
precisely because we're all unreasonable people
进步就靠我们这种人改变世界  来靠拢我们
and progress depends on our changing the world to fit us.
而不是倒过来
Not the other way around.
我想相信这点
I want to believe that.
我必须相信
I must believe that.
明天  我会早上7点来上班
Tomorrow, I will show up at 7:00 A.M.
我会继续前进
and I will keep going.
你们不非得来
You don't have to join me, but...
但我觉得
something tells me
你们都跟我一样需要这个
you both need this just as much as I do.
史上最棒的一场比赛
Greatest game ever played?
小时候  我爸会把那个当睡前故事讲
My dad used to tell me bedtime stories about it as a kid.
加时  雷蒙德·巴里12个接球什么的
Overtime, Raymond Berry's 12 receptions, all that.
比赛是在58年12月
The game was December '58.
旅行者1号近一年前就下来了
Sputnik came down almost a year before that.
是吗
Is that right?
人人影视
倾情奉献
翻译
CiciXT
磁芯章鱼X
翻译
木浅薰
somehacker
翻译
某豚
冬麟
翻译
天朝直属
草草好喜欢卡梅伦
时间轴
Kallen 芒果树叶
特效
宝宝
电脑狂人
第一季
第二集
校对&总监
草草
后期
饿得慌
顾问
大伟昔